http://quicklinks.qlinks.net/search/label/Data%20protection%20%2F%20privacy

skip to main
|
skip to sidebar
QuickLinks
Links to news items about legal and regulatory aspects of Internet and the information society
Showing posts with label Data protection / privacy. Show all posts
Showing posts with label Data protection / privacy. Show all posts
23 February 2012
Broken Promises of Privacy: Responding to the Surprising Failure of Anonymization
(UCLA Law Review) by Paul Ohm, University of Colorado Law School. Computer scientists have recently undermined our faith in the privacy-protecting power of anonymization, the name for techniques for protecting the privacy of individuals in large databases by deleting information like names and social security numbers. These scientists have demonstrated they can often 'reidentify' or 'deanonymize' individuals hidden in anonymized data with astonishing ease. By understanding this research, we will realize we have made a mistake, labored beneath a fundamental misunderstanding, which has assured us much less privacy than we have assumed. This mistake pervades nearly every information privacy law, regulation, and debate, yet regulators and legal scholars have paid it scant attention. We must respond to the surprising failure of anonymization, and this Article provides the tools to do so.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
26 January 2012
EU - Commission proposes a comprehensive reform of data protection rules
(RAPID)
The European Commission has proposed a comprehensive reform of the EU's data protection rules. The Commission's proposals update and modernise the principles enshrined in the 1995 Data Protection Directive to guarantee privacy rights in the future. They include a policy Communication setting out the Commission's objectives and two legislative proposals: a Regulation setting out a general EU framework for data protection and a Directive on protecting personal data processed for the purposes of prevention, detection, investigation or prosecution of criminal offences and related judicial activities.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
05 July 2011
High level discussions on online tracking
(EDRI-gram)
A meeting organised jointly by the University of Berkeley and the Institute for Information Law of the University of Amsterdam drew together an outstanding collection of international experts, NGOs and industry representatives to discuss online tracking protection and browsers.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
22 May 2011
FR - Comment concilier la protection de la vie privée et la réutilisation des archives publiques sur internet ?
(CNIL) La CNIL est souvent confrontée aux difficultés soulevées par l'application combinée de la loi informatique et libertés, de la loi CADA et du code du patrimoine. C´est pourquoi elle a précisé dans une recommandation dans sa recommandation du 9 décembre 2010, les cas dans lesquels la réutilisation de données personnelles contenues dans des documents d´archives est à exclure. Elle a également rappelé, pour les cas où cette réutilisation est possible, les précautions à prendre.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy,
E-government
EU - Location data should qualify as personal data, watchdogs say
(OUT-LAW News) The Article 29 Working Party has said that geolocation information on where a person has been should qualify as personal data and be protected by EU data protection laws. It said that users should be asked to consent to every new use of the data.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy,
Location-based services
10 May 2011
UK - ICO publishes advice on how websites can comply with new 'cookie law'
(OUT-LAW News) Websites should not rely on browser settings as indicating whether a user consents to having their online activity tracked, the Information Commission's Office (ICO) has advised.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
06 April 2011
FR - Conservation des données sur Internet : l'Asic se fâche
(ZDNet France)
Les grands noms de l´Internet s´associent derrière l´Asic pour demander l´annulation du décret qui impose aux sites web, aux réseaux sociaux, aux gestionnaires de boîtes mail de conserver un an durant les données de leurs utilisateurs. Les membres de l'Association des Services Internet Communautaires (ASIC) déposeront un recours en annulation devant le Conseil d'Etat. Les acteurs de l'internet contestent massivement un décret paru au journal officiel le 1er mars dernier, visant à obliger les sites à conserver pendant un an: "les nom et prénoms" de leurs clients, "les adresses postales associées", "les pseudonymes utilisés", "les adresses de courrier électronique ou de compte associées", "les numéros de téléphone" ou encore "le mot de passe ainsi que les données permettant de le vérifier ou de le modifier".
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
24 March 2011
EU - The Privacy Platform Meeting: Reding outlines the way forward
(EDRI-gram)
On 16 March 2011, Sophie In't Veld's Privacy Platform met in the European Parliament to discuss the state of play for the review of the data protection directive. In her keynote speech, Ms. Reding said that data protection was her "top legislative priority". She plans to enhance control and build individual rights in four pillars: 1. The right to be forgotten. Individuals have the right to withdraw consent to data processing, and it will be up to the data controllers to prove the need to collect or retain personal data. 2. Greater transparency. For data subjects, the use, collection and retention of personal data must be made clear, intelligible, easy to understand and easy to find. She made particular reference to social networking services and children. 3. The third pillar is "privacy by default". Privacy settings often require considerable operational effort in order to be put in place. Such settings are not a reliable indication of consumers' consent. This needs to be changed. 4. Data protection regardless of data location. The data subject will enjoy protection, independent of the geographical region where the data is being collected and processed, without exception for third-party providers. See Commissioner Reding's keynote speech, Your data, your rights: safeguarding your rights in a connected world.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
16 March 2011
EU to force social network sites to enhance privacy
(Guardian) The European Union is to enshrine a "right to be forgotten online" to ensure that, among other things, prospective employers cannot find old Facebook party photos of someone wearing nothing but a lampshade. In a speech to the European parliament, the EU justice commissioner, Viviane Reding, warned companies such as Facebook that: "A US-based social network company that has millions of active users in Europe needs to comply with EU rules."
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
22 January 2011
EU - Data Protection Reform Strategy: EDPS sets out his vision
(RAPID)
On 14 January 2011, the European Data Protection Supervisor (EDPS) issued an opinion on the Commission's Communication on the review of the EU legal framework for data protection. The EDPS suggests introducing a mandatory security breach notification covering all relevant sectors, as well as new rights, especially in the online environment, such as the right to be forgotten (to have one's data deleted or not further disseminated after a fixed period of time) and data portability (the ability to shift data from one place to another and not be tied to a particular system). Children's data should also be better protected.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
20 January 2011
ES - Google fights Spanish privacy order in court
(BBC)
Google has challenged Spain's data protection agency, the AEPD, in court over claims that its search engine invades personal privacy. The regulator had told the internet giant to delete links to websites that contain out of date or inaccurate information about individuals. But the company argues that it is publishers - and not search engines - that should be forced to take action. The case revolves around a ruling that some search results contravene the country's privacy laws.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
16 January 2011
Why 'Web Erasers' Can't Work
(Spiegel)
As part of its pitch to give people more personal privacy on the Web, the German government is encouraging development of software that sets expiration dates on photos and other private information.At the invitation of the German government, an IT professor has introduced software that allows people to set an expiration date for photos they post on Facebook or other sites. What it can't do, however, is prevent others from copying or stealing a person's personal data and posting it wherever they want on the Internet.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
24 December 2010
The Single Greatest Chart Ever (At Least if You Want to Know Where Your Personal Information Goes)
(ACLU)
The Federal Trade Commission (FTC) released a report (PDF) that provides an outstanding start on describing the problems of data collection both on and offline. Buried in that FTC report is a small gem: On pages 107 and 108 is Appendix C, a chart prepared by technologist Richard Smith which conveys all of the personal information collected about all of us and where it goes.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
17 December 2010
US administration proposes 'bill of rights' to protect online privacy
(OUT-LAW News)
The administration of US President Barack Obama may turn its back on its policy of allowing online publishers and advertisers to self-regulate and is proposing Government intervention to protect internet users' privacy. The Department of Commerce has published a report (88-page / 1MB PDF) recommending the creation of a privacy 'bill of rights' for internet users; mandatory privacy codes of conduct; and legal reform to take account of cloud computing. The Department of Commerce's policy framework says that the US Government should "consider establishing fair information practice principles comparable to a 'privacy bill of rights' for online consumers; consider developing enforceable privacy codes of conduct in specific sectors with stakeholders; create a Privacy Policy Office in the Department of Commerce"; [and] review the Electronic Communications Privacy Act for the cloud computing environment.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
01 December 2010
Why the EU needs new personal data protection rules
(RAPID)
Speech by Viviane Reding Vice-President of the European Commission, responsible for Justice, Fundamental Rights and Citizenship Privacy matters, The European Data Protection and Privacy Conference Brussels, 30 November 2010. I want to introduce the "right to be forgotten". Social network sites are a great way to stay in touch with friends and share information. But if people no longer want to use a service, they should have no problem wiping out their profiles. The right to be forgotten is particularly relevant to personal data that is no longer needed for the purposes for which it was collected. This right should also apply when a storage period, which the user agreed to, has expired. Existing legislation has led to divergences between the national laws. Even when there is only one European issue, there is not always one European response. Take the example of Google StreetView and the collection of snippets of personal information from unsecured WiFi networks. This did not only prompt different responses by national data protection authorities but it also led the company to provide different remedies for individuals in different Member States. This situation runs counter to both of the two main objectives of the existing Data Protection Directive: ensuring the protection of a fundamental right and ensuring the free flow of personal data within the Single Market.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
25 November 2010
EU - Cloud computing and data protection
(RAPID)
Speech by Neelie Kroes, European Commission Vice-President for the Digital Agenda, Les Assises du Numérique conference, Université Paris-Dauphine, 25 November 2010. As summarised on Neelie Kroes' Twitter feed: Clear and robust data protection is a "must have" feature for cloud services. We we all deserve 2 things: 1) cloud suppliers protect personal data efficiently and transparently and 2) countries hosting cloud servers must have laws guaranteeing data protection with any limited security exceptions governed by rule of law.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
20 November 2010
The Trouble with Facebook's 'See Friendship' Feature
(Time)
Facebook normally catches flack for making private information available to advertisers. But last month, the social-networking site with half a billion users quietly added a feature that makes your private information available to the friends of your friends, which may be a much more nefarious group. A button called "See Friendship" aggregates onto a single page all of the information that two friends share: photos both people have been tagged in, events they have attended or are planning to attend, comments they have exchanged, etc.
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
12 November 2010
Serfing the web - Data protectionism
(Economist)
A small spat highlights a big issue: who owns your online identity?
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
05 November 2010
UK - Information Commissioner will not fine Google over Wi-Fi data gathering
(OUT-LAW News)
UK privacy watchdog the Information Commissioner will not fine Google over unauthorised collection of personal data by its Street View cars, despite ruling that this was a "significant breach of the Data Protection Act". Google sent cars with roof-mounted cameras around the UK's cities last year to photograph the streets for its photo-map Street View service. Research by the Canadian Privacy Commissioner revealed that significant personal information, including whole emails; usernames; passwords; and addresses were gathered and stored by Google. The ICO has now announced that it will take some action against the company, but will stop short of imposing fines. Instead, Google will be made to sign an undertaking to improve its data protection practices and will face an audit of existing policies and practices. see also Google Street View has got off lightly (Guardian).
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
04 November 2010
EU - European Commission sets out strategy to strengthen EU data protection rules
(Europa)
Controlling your information, having access to your data, being able to modify or delete it – these are essential rights that have to be guaranteed in today's digital world. To address these issues, the European Commission today set out a strategy on how to protect individuals' data in all policy areas, including law enforcement, while reducing red tape for business and guaranteeing the free circulation of data within the EU. This policy review will be used by the Commission with the results of a public consultation to revise the EU’s 1995 Data Protection Directive. The Commission will then propose legislation in 2011. Under the review, data retained for law enforcement purposes should also be covered by the new legislative framework. The Commission is also reviewing the 2006 Data Retention Directive, under which companies are required to store communication traffic data for a period of between six months and two years. The Commission is calling on all stakeholders and the public to comment on the review's proposals until 15 January 2011. See also 'Right to be forgotten' proposed by European Commission
(Daily Telegraph).
Labels:
Data protection / privacy
Older Posts
Home
Subscribe to:
Posts (Atom)
June 2015 (1)
October 2014 (1)
August 2014 (1)
December 2013 (2)
December 2012 (1)
August 2012 (2)
July 2012 (9)
May 2012 (1)
April 2012 (1)
March 2012 (1)
February 2012 (1)
January 2012 (2)
December 2011 (1)
November 2011 (2)
October 2011 (1)
September 2011 (3)
August 2011 (5)
July 2011 (9)
June 2011 (5)
May 2011 (22)
April 2011 (5)
March 2011 (28)
February 2011 (18)
January 2011 (31)
December 2010 (20)
November 2010 (48)
October 2010 (30)
September 2010 (42)
August 2010 (29)
July 2010 (35)
June 2010 (65)
May 2010 (45)
April 2010 (50)
March 2010 (62)
February 2010 (65)
January 2010 (26)
December 2009 (68)
November 2009 (58)
October 2009 (37)
September 2009 (35)
August 2009 (21)
July 2009 (88)
June 2009 (56)
May 2009 (28)
April 2009 (30)
March 2009 (44)
February 2009 (65)
January 2009 (36)
December 2008 (41)
November 2008 (41)
October 2008 (50)
September 2008 (44)
August 2008 (31)
July 2008 (47)
June 2008 (65)
May 2008 (102)
April 2008 (53)
March 2008 (74)
February 2008 (70)
January 2008 (109)
December 2007 (51)
November 2007 (31)
October 2007 (36)
September 2007 (75)
August 2007 (88)
July 2007 (44)
June 2007 (75)
May 2007 (65)
April 2007 (48)
March 2007 (52)
February 2007 (78)
January 2007 (48)
December 2006 (64)
November 2006 (76)
October 2006 (92)
September 2006 (83)
August 2006 (131)
July 2006 (36)
June 2006 (110)
May 2006 (88)
April 2006 (63)
March 2006 (98)
February 2006 (95)
January 2006 (64)
December 2005 (76)
November 2005 (76)
October 2005 (138)
September 2005 (98)
August 2005 (77)
July 2005 (61)
June 2005 (58)
May 2005 (43)
April 2005 (116)
March 2005 (88)
February 2005 (88)
January 2005 (87)
December 2004 (66)
November 2004 (85)
October 2004 (113)
September 2004 (93)
August 2004 (131)
July 2004 (146)
June 2004 (121)
May 2004 (151)
April 2004 (74)
March 2004 (89)
February 2004 (120)
January 2004 (171)
December 2003 (189)
November 2003 (181)
October 2003 (214)
September 2003 (191)
August 2003 (219)
July 2003 (83)
June 2003 (127)
May 2003 (197)
April 2003 (182)
March 2003 (143)
February 2003 (98)
January 2003 (106)
December 2002 (112)
November 2002 (189)
October 2002 (130)
September 2002 (219)
August 2002 (77)
July 2002 (216)
June 2002 (235)
May 2002 (228)
April 2002 (249)
March 2002 (224)
February 2002 (256)
January 2002 (238)
December 2001 (231)
November 2001 (240)
October 2001 (262)
September 2001 (240)
August 2001 (178)
July 2001 (475)
June 2001 (313)
May 2001 (323)
April 2001 (124)
March 2001 (292)
February 2001 (234)
January 2001 (218)
December 2000 (234)
November 2000 (265)
October 2000 (247)
September 2000 (167)
August 2000 (178)
July 2000 (381)
June 2000 (351)
May 2000 (287)
April 2000 (138)
March 2000 (338)
February 2000 (368)
January 2000 (256)
December 1999 (461)
November 1999 (40)
